# HAROON RASHID LONE

LINK LAB, University of Virginia, Email: haroon.it@gmail.com
Charlottesville, VA-22904, USA Alt.: hl7ck@virginia.edu
Website: http://loneharoon.github.io GitHub: https://github.com/loneharoon

# RESEARCH INTERESTS

Internet-of-Things (IoT), Machine Learning, Data Science, Energy Sustainability, Smart Healthcare

# CURRENT RESEARCH WORK AT LINK LAB, UVA

I work as a Postdoctoral Researcher in an interdisciplinary project between Engineering, Psychology, and Environment departments of the UVA. The idea is to leverage wearables and mobile technology in identifying digital biomarkers for the detection of social anxiety in college students under natural settings.

# **EDUCATION**

Indraprastha Institute of Information Technology Delhi (IIIT-D) Ph.D. in Computer Science	Delhi, India 2014 – 2019
National Institute of Technology Rourkela	Odisha, India
Master's in Computer Science	2011 – 2013
University of Jammu	Jammu, India
Bachelor's in Information Technology	2006 – 2010

## PhD THESIS

Title: Detecting Anomalous Energy Consumption in Buildings Using Smart Meter Data Advisor: Prof. Pushpendra Singh

## This thesis

- Presents techniques for identifying electrical energy wastage instances in buildings using smart-meters
- Evaluates energy disaggregation approaches for identifying appliances causing energy wastage
- Produces a four-year context-rich energy dataset collected from seven buildings of IIIT Delhi

#### MASTER'S THESIS

Title: Localization in Wireless Sensor Networks

Advisor: Prof. Ashok K. Turuk

This thesis presents techniques for localizing mobile wireless sensor nodes with minimum number of beacon nodes installed with a GPS unit.

## WORK EXPERIENCE

Postdoctoral Researcher, University of Virginia Virginia, USA

\*Advisor: Prof. Laura Barnes May, 2019 - Present

Visiting Researcher, University of Strathclyde Scotland, UK Advisors: Prof. Vladimir Stankovic, Prof. Lina Stankovic Nov., 2017 - April, 2018

Visiting Researcher, IIT Bombay Mumbai, India Advisor: Prof. Krithi Ramamritham Oct. - Dec., 2016

Research Associate, IIIT Delhi Delhi, India Advisor: Prof. Pushpendra Singh Aug. - Dec., 2013

# **PUBLICATIONS**

#### **Journals**

- H. Rashid, P. Singh, A. Singh. "I-BLEND, a Campus Scale Commercial and Residential Buildings Electrical Energy Dataset," *Scientific Data, Nature*, 2019.[Impact factor = 6.7]
- H. Rashid, P. Singh, V. Stankovic, L. Stankovic. "Can Non-intrusive Load Monitoring be Used for Identifying an Appliances Anomalous Behaviour?" Applied Energy, Elsevier, 2019. [Impact factor = 7.9]
- H. Rashid, A. K. Turuk. "Dead Reckoning Localization Technique for Mobile Wireless Sensor Networks," *IET Wireless Sensor Systems*, 5(2), 2014. [CiteScore = 2.2]
- H. Rashid, A. K. Turuk. "Localization of Wireless Sensor Networks Using a Single Anchor Node," Wireless Personal communications Springer, 72(2), 2013. [Impact factor = 0.9]

## Conferences

- H. Rashid, V. Stankovic, L. Stankovic, P. Singh. "Evaluation of Non-Intrusive Load Monitoring Algorithms for Appliance-level Anomaly Detection," *IEEE ICASSP*, Brighton, UK, 2019.
- H. Rashid, N. Batra, P. Singh. "Rimor: Towards Identifying Anomalous Appliances in Buildings," *ACM BuildSys'18*, Shenzen, China, 2018. [Acceptance rate = 37%]
- H. Rashid, P. Singh. "Monitor: An Abnormality Detection Approach in Buildings Energy Consumption," *IEEE CIC'18*, Philadelphia, USA, 2018. [Acceptance rate = 26%]
- P. M. Mammen, H. Kumar, K. Ramamritham, **H. Rashid**. "Want to Reduce Energy Consumption, Whom should we call," *ACM e-Energy'18*, Karlsruhe, Germany, 2018. [Acceptance rate = 22%]
- H. Rashid, P. M. Mammen, S. Singh, K. Ramamritham, P. Singh, P. Shenoy. "Want to Reduce Energy Consumption? Don't Depend on the Consumers!" *ACM BuildSys'17*, Delft, The Netherlands, 2017. [Acceptance rate = 31%]
- H. Rashid, P. Singh, K. Ramamritham. "Revisiting Selection of Residential Consumers for Demand Response Programs," ACM BuildSys'17, Delft, The Netherlands, 2017. [Acceptance rate = 31%]

# Posters

- H. Rashid, P. Singh. "Energy Disaggregation for Identifying Anomalous Appliance," ACM BuildSys'17, poster session, Delft, The Netherlands, 2017.
- H. Rashid, P. Arjuna, P. Singh, A. Singh. "Collect, Compare, and Score: A Generic Data-driven Anomaly Detection Method for Buildings," *ACM e-Energy'16, poster session*, Waterloo, Canada, 2016.

# HONOURS & AWARDS

- Received Microsoft travel grant for BuildSys 2018
- Received SIGMOBILE travel grant for BuildSys 2017
- Received TCS Research Fellowship for a duration of 5 years
- Qualified GATE 2011 in Computer Science and Engineering with 96.14 percentile

# UNDERGRADUATE TEACHING EXPERIENCE

- Teaching Assistant. Computer Networks, with Prof. Pushpendra Singh, Fall 2018, IIIT-Delhi.
- Teaching Assistant. Advanced Programming, with Prof. Manish Sharotiya, Fall 2014, IIIT-Delhi.
- Lab Assistant. C++, with Prof. A. K. Turuk, Spring 2013, NIT Rourkela.
- Lab Assistant. Data Structure, with Prof. Ramesh Mohapatra, Fall 2012, NIT Rourkela.
- Lab Assistant. System Analysis and Design Lab, with Prof. Sujata Mohanty, Spring 2012, NIT Rourkela.

## REFERENCES

## Pushpendra Singh

Professor Dept. of CSE IIIT-Delhi New Delhi-110020, India psingh@iiitd.ac.in

#### Krithi Ramamritham

Professor Dept. of CSE IIT Bombay Bombay-400076, India krithi@cse.iitb.ac.in

#### Vladimir Stankovic

Reader Dept. of EE University of Strathclyde Glasgow - G1 1XW, UK vladimir.stankovic@strath.ac.uk

#### Lina Stankovic

Lecturer
Dept. of EE
University of Strathclyde
Glasgow - G1 1XW, UK
lina.stankovic@strath.ac.uk

#### Laura Barnes

Associate professor Dept. of Engineering Sytems University of Virginia Charlottesville - VA, USA lb3dp@virginia.edu